Eisig Silberschlag papers M1479
Stanford University. Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Eisig Silberschlag Papers
1910-1989
M1479
Stanford University. Department of Special Collections and University Archives
27.0 Linear feet
Manuscripts, correspondence, photographs, clippings, photocopies, writings by others, and ephemera, ca. 1920s to 1980s. Box 52, containing personal correspondence between Eisig Silberschlag and Dalia Daniel and a small number of photographs, ca. 1973-1986, is closed to public access until 2016.
Biographical/Historical Note
Eisig Silberschlag was born in 1903 in the city of Stryy, located in what is now Ukraine. In 1925 he received a doctorate from the University of Bienna, and, over the course of his long career, was considered an authority in the field of Hebrew literary criticism. Silberschlag was an accomplished poet who translated Aristophanes and Menander from Greek into Hebrew. In 1944 he joined the faculty of Hebrew College of Boston and was named dean in 1947. In the late 1960s, his title was changed to president. In 1951, Silberschlag won the Tschernichowsky Prize of the Municipality of Tel Aviv for his translations of the comedies of Aristophanes. He also received the Florence Kovner Memorial Award in 1971 for a book of poems, LETTERS TO OTHER GENERATIONS. After his retirement from Hebrew College in 1970, he moved to Austin, Texas, where he was appointed professor of Judaic studies at the University of Texas. He died in Austin in 1988
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2005. Accession 2005-202.
Access Note
Open for research; material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Box 52 is closed until 2036.
Scope and Contents Note
Manuscripts, correspondence, photographs, clippings, photocopies, writings by others, and ephemera, ca. 1920s to 1980s.
- Series I. Clippings, photocopies, 2.0 Boxes
  - Clippings and photocopies (1 of 2) (Carton 1)
  - Clippings and photocopies (2 of 2) (Carton 2)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Subseries A: Incoming, 31.0 Boxes
    - Adm-Bavli, 21.0 Folders (Box 3)
      - Admirers, female
      - Agnon, S.Y.
      - Alter, Robert
      - Altmann, Alexander
      - Am Oved Publishing
      - Amichai, Yehuda (1 letter)
      - Ankori, Zvi
      - Arendt, Hannah/Jewish Cultural Reconstruction, Inc. (1 letter)
      - Attorney General of Texas
      - Atzmon, Ezri
      - Barkai du-shavuon
      - Barash, Asher
      - Baron, Jeannette
      - Baron, Salo/Jewish Social Studies
      - Barzel, Aviva
      - Barzilai, Y.
      - Bass, S.
      - Bavli, Hillel
    - Ben G-Bran, 18.0 Folders (Box 4)
      - Ben Gurion, David (2 letters)
      - Ben-Menachem, Naphtali
      - Ben-Tzion, Tsevi
      - Ben-Yishai, A.Z./Tel Aviv Municipality
      - Ben Yosef, Reuven
      - Berman, Herbert
      - Bernstein, Shimon
      - Bialik Institute
      - Bitzaron/Chaim Tsernowitz
      - Blumenfeld, Samuel
      - Boyd, Esther
      - Brainin, Joseph (son of Reuben Brainin; 1 letter)
      - Brandeis University/Albert Einstein birthday dinner
      - Brandmark, E. (Stryj)
    - Brau-Dan, 19.0 Folders (Carton 5)
      - Braude, William (1 note)
      - Braunschwig, Jules
      - E.J. Brill
      - Brit ivrit olamit
      - Brownstone, Minka (Milka's sister)
      - Broyda, Alexander
      - Buber, Martin (1 note)
      - Cassirer, Eva
      - Central Yiddish Cultural Org.
      - Charney, Daniel
      - Cohen, Israel
      - Collier's
      - Columbia University
      - Commission on Jewish Education
      - Contemporary Jewish Record/Commentary
      - Cooper, Harry D. Estate
      - Cornell University Press
      - Daniel, Dalia/Yitshak Ros (Daniel's father)
    - Dav-Fuchs, 24.0 Folders (Box 6)
      - Davar
      - David, Yonah
      - Diezendruck, Zvi
      - Duker, Abraham
      - Dvir
      - East and West Library
      - Eban, Abba
      - Eisenberg, Azriel
      - Eked Publishers
      - Emmanuel College
      - Entin, Moses
      - Farmelant, Annabelle
      - Federbusch, Simon/Histadruth Ivrith of America
      - Feig, Irena
      - Feigin, Samuel
      - Feinstein, Moses
      - Feldman, Yael
      - Fine, Jacob
      - Finkelstein, Louis
      - Fischel, Henry
      - Forster-Nietsche, Elisabeth
      - Friedman, Nathan
      - Fuchs, Esther
    - Gale-Green, 19.0 Folders (Box 7)
      - Gale, Edwin
      - Gannes, Abe/Dept. of Education and Culture, Jewish Agency
      - Ginzburg, Simon
      - Glatzer, Nahum
      - Glueck, Sheldon
      - Goitein, S.D.
      - Golan, Shamai
      - Goldberg, Abraham
      - Goldberg, Maurice (3 musical scores w/inscription)
      - Goldberg, Maxwell
      - Goldman, Solomon
      - Goldmann, Nahum
      - Goodman, Philip/Jewish Book Council of America
      - Goss, Isaac/South African Board of Jewish Education
      - Govrin, Nurith
      - Grad, Eli
      - Grayzel, Solomon (JPS)
      - Greenwald, Norman/American College in Jerusalem
    - Gress-Haehl, 13.0 Folders (Box 8)
      - Gresser, Gisele
      - Groepper, Tamina (Haehling)
      - Gross, Chaim
      - Grossinger, Hermine
      - Haberman, A.M.
      - Habimah
      - Hadoar
      - Haehling, Tamina V. (aka Groepper)
    - Halkin-HTC, 10.0 Folders (Box 9)
      - Halkin, Simon
      - Hantke, J.T.
      - Hareli, Shaul/Jewish Agency for Palestine
      - Hazaz, Haim & Aviva
      - Hebrew Culture Society
      - Hebrew PEN Club
      - Hebrew Teachers College/Hebrew College
    - HTC-Hurwitz, 12.0 Folders (Box 10)
      - Hebrew Teachers College/Hebrew College
      - Hebrew Union College/Jewish Institute of Religion
      - Hebrew University
      - Helman, Edith
      - Horch, Franz J.
      - Hourani, Albert
      - Hurston, Zora Neale (3 letters, 1937)
      - Hurwich, Leah/Women's School of Jewish Studies
      - Hurwich, Louis
      - Hurwitz, Henry/Menorah Journal
    - Indel-Kafka, 16.0 Folders (Box 11)
      - Indelman, Elhanan
      - International Microfiche Center/Henry L. de Mink
      - Israel Matz Foundation (re: David Vogel)
      - Ivask, Ivar/World Literature Today
      - Ivry, Isaac
      - Jacobs, Leo
      - Jacobs, Rose/Hadassah
      - Jaffe, Mordecai
      - Janowsky, Oscar
      - Jewish Palestine Exploration Society
      - Jewish Publication Society
      - Jewish Social Studies
      - Jewish Theological Seminary
      - Kabakoff, Jacob
      - Kafka research correspondence
    - Kahn, 5.0 Folders (Box 12)
      - Kahn, Charlotte (E.S.'s secretary at HTC)
    - Katsch-Lown, 18.0 Folders (Box 13)
      - Katsch, Abraham
      - Katzir, Ephraim
      - Klatzkin, Jacob
      - Klausner, Joseph
      - Kohut, George
      - Kuselwitz, David
      - Lamdan, Yitshak
      - Leaf, Haim
      - Lehman, Emil
      - Lehner, Fredrick
      - Library of Congress
      - Lieberman, Saul
      - Lipts, D
      - Loewe, Raphael
      - Louis LaMed Foundation
      - Lown, Linda
      - Lown, Philip
    - Lucius-NAPH, 14.0 Folders (Box 14)
      - Lucius N. Littauer Foundation
      - Malachi, A.R.
      - Malachi, Zvi
      - Mansoor, Menachem
      - Marwick, Lawrence
      - Massadah Publishing
      - Mehlmann, Israel
      - Miron, Dan
      - Moznayim
      - Naamani, Israel
      - Nakarai, Toyozo
      - Name & address list ca. 1930s
      - National Association of Professors of Hebrew
    - NEH-Ozick, 13.0 Folders (Box 15)
      - National Endowment for the Humanities/Irene U. Burnham
      - Niger, Shemuel
      - Netanyahu, Ben Tsiyon (father of Yonatan and Binyamin)
      - Neuman, Abraham/Dropsie College
      - Newman, Mordecai
      - Nussenblatt, T. (Vienna, 1937)
      - Obermann, Julian
      - Oxford Centre for Postgraduate Hebrew Studies
      - Ozick, Cynthia (2 notes)
    - Patai-Ravid, 9.0 Folders (Box 16)
      - Patai, Raphael
      - Patterson, David/Oxford Centre for Postgraduate Hebrew Studies
      - Pelli, Moshe
      - PEN American Center
      - PEN Centre in Israel
      - Perls, Hugo & Eugenie
      - Persky, Daniel
      - Pinson, Koppel/Jewish Social Studies
      - Potok, Chaim/JPS
      - Preil, Gabriel
      - Rabin, Chaim
      - Rabinovits, Yeshayah
      - Raisin, Max
      - Ravid, Zevulun
    - Poet Lore, 8.0 Folders (Box 17)
      - Correspondence A-Z and notes
    - Hatekufah: Correspondence A-Z & notes, 36.0 Folders (Box 18)
      - Agnon
      - Baron, Salo
      - Hatekufah blank stationery
      - Zeitlin, Aharon
      - Weinryb, Bernard
      - Twersky, Y.
      - Tartakower, Aryeh
      - Stybel
      - Silberschlag
      - Shulsinger Bros.
      - Shalom, Sh.
      - Sackler, S.
      - Ribalow, Menahem
      - Raisin, Max
      - Preil, Gabriel
      - Niger, Shemuel
      - Halkin, S.
      - Finkelstein, Eliezer
      - Fikhman, Y.
      - Feigin, S.
      - Brownstone, Miriam (Minka)
      - Bavli, Hillel
    - Rawid-Scharf, 15.0 Folders (Box 19)
      - Rawidowicz, Simon
      - The Reconstructionist
      - A. Regelson Publishing Co.
      - Rubin Mas Publishing Co.
      - Ribalow, Menahem
      - Rice University
      - Riklis, Y.
      - Rivkind, I.
      - Roth, Cecil/Encyclopedia Hebraica
      - Sackler, Harry (2 folders)
      - Sarna, Nahum
      - Saron, G./South Africa visit, 1963
      - Savitz, Harry
      - Scharfstein, Bernard
    - Schock-Shvarts, 22.0 Folders (Box 20)
      - Schocken, Salman
      - Schoville, Keith
      - Schor, Ilya
      - Schreier, Isaac
      - Schwartz, Maurice/Yiddish Art Theatre
      - Schwarz, Leo
      - Seeman, Jakob
      - Seitz-Diamond, Gosia
      - Selekman, B.M.
      - Shalom, Sh.
      - Sharet, Moshe
      - Shazar, Zalman
      - Shenberg, Yitzhak/Schocken Library, Jerusalem
      - Shneour, Eli
      - Shneour, Zalman
      - Sholem, Gershom
      - Shrier, Pauline
      - Shulsinger Bros. Printing
      - Shvarts-Nardi, Shulamit
    - Silber-Spiegel, 14.0 Folders (Box 21)
      - Silber, John R.
      - Silkiner, Benjamin Nahum (1 postcard)
      - Silver, Bertha (mother)
      - Silver, Henry (brother)
      - Silver, Sidney (brother, born Zallel Sternbach)
      - Slutzki, Aryeh
      - Smilansky, Yizhar
      - Smolar, Boris
      - Snowe, Edna
      - Solodar, A./Dorenu
      - South African Board of Jewish Deputies
      - Spiegel, Shalom
    - Stadt-Tshern, 16.0 Folders (Box 22)
      - Stadtler, Bea
      - Standard Jewish Encyclopedia
      - Steinberg, Paul M.
      - Steiner, M.
      - Steinman, E.
      - Stevens, Claudine
      - Strauss, Leo
      - Strelka, Joseph
      - Sybel, Avraham
      - Tancer (Baron) Family
      - Tartakower, Aryeh
      - Teatron Kameri
      - Toren, Haim
      - Touroff, Nissan
      - Tshernowitz, Chaim
    - Tsukunft-Zeitlin, 26.0 Folders (Box 23)
      - Di Tsukunft
      - Tversky, Yitshak
      - United Publishers Association
      - Vogel, David
      - Wallenrod, Reuven
      - Wallenstein, Meir
      - Weinreich, Max
      - Weinstein, Lewis
      - Wiesel, Elie (1 note)
      - Wilensky, Mordechai
      - Wilfand, Yosef
      - Wilson, Edmund
      - Wise, Stephen
      - Wolfson, Harry
      - World Jewish Congress
      - World Zionist Organization
      - WPA Federal Theatre Project
      - Writers' War Board
      - Yaari, Yehudah
      - Yad Vashem/Hadassah Modlinger (query about ES WWII diary)
      - Yahuda, A.S.
      - Zeitlin, Aaron
      - Zeitlin, Solomon/Jewish Quarterly Review
    - UT Austin A-L, 16.0 Folders (Box 24)
      - Berlin, Charles (Baron Collection appraisal; HC board member)
      - Bill, James A.
      - British Studies
      - Center for Middle East Studies
      - Department of Oriental & African Languages & Literatures (DOALL)
      - English, Paul W.
      - Fishman, Charles/Houston JCC
      - Flyers/Press releases
      - Hillel Foundation
      - King, Robert D.
      - Lieb, Irwin C.
    - UT Austin M-W, 10.0 Folders (Box 25)
      - Werbow, Stanley N.
      - Spurr, Stephen H.
      - Rostow, Elspeth D.
      - Ross, Stanley R.
      - Polombe, Edgar C.
      - Miscellaneous correspondence
      - Middleton, Christopher
      - Mersky, Roy
    - Box 26 Misc., 7.0 Folders (Box 26)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, before 1970
    - Misc., 8.0 Folders (Box 27)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, before 1970
    - Misc., 6.0 Folders (Box 28)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, before 1970
    - Misc., 6.0 Folders (Box 29)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1970 and after
    - Misc., 10.0 Folders (Box 30)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1970 and after
    - Misc., 7.0 Folders (Box 31)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1970 and after
  - Subseries B: Outgoing
    - before 1940, 6.0 Folders (Box 32)
    - 1970 and after, 6.0 Folders (Box 33)
- Series III. Administrative and Pedagogical
  - Emmanuel College; Hebrew Teachers College; UT Austin, 8.0 Folders (Box 34)
  - Hebrew Teachers College, 3.0 Folders (Box 35)
- Series IV. Manuscripts, notes, and writings
  - "Russisch-Englische Beziehungen Waehrend der Regierungszeit Katharinas II," n.d., ca. 1920s, 4.0 Folders (Box 36)
  - "Hebrew Poetry in the Twentieth Century," n.d.; 100+ p. letter to unidentified female friend, n.d. ca. 1920s, 9.0 Folders (Box 37)
  - Biographical sketch, part of untitled play, 11.0 Folders (Box 38)
  - E.S. translation from Greek into Hebrew: "Komedyot shel Aristofanes," and related clippings and correspondence (Box 39)
  - Writings, notes, and clippings related to S.Y. Agnon, 14.0 Folders (Box 40)
  - Unsorted notes, writings, and clippings (Box 41)
  - Unsorted notes, writings, and clippings (Box 42)
  - Unsorted notes, writings, and clippings (Carton 43)
  - Unsorted notes, writings, and clippings (Carton 44)
  - Unsorted notes, writings, and clippings (Carton 45)
  - Unsorted notes, writings, and clippings (Carton 66)
  - Unsorted notes, writings, and clippings (Carton 67)
  - Unsorted notes, writings, and clippings (Carton 55)
- Series V. Milka Silberschlag
  - Correspondence and writings, 12.0 (Box 46)
  - Medical documents, writing, condolence letters following Milka Silberschlag's death., 5.0 Folders (Box 47)
- Series VI. Notebooks, diaries, and calendars
  - Notebooks, diaries, and calendars, 13.0 Folders (Carton 48)
  - Notebooks, diaries, and calendars, 4.0 Folders (Box 49)
  - Scrapbook containing clippings, ca. 1940s
- Series VII. Offprints
  - Publications by Silberschlag (Carton 51)
  - Publications by other authors (Carton 68)
- Series VIII. Personal
  - Banking/insurance/investments/pay stubs; Hotels/travel; Household; Membership cards, 14.0 Folders (Box 53)
  - Draft classification cards; Ephemera; Medical; Naturalization; Passports; School documents; Silberschlag, Milka (legal-size documents); Silver, Bertha and Henry Silver; Silver, Sidney (Zallel Sternbach); Travel, 11.0 Folders (Box 54)
  - Shofar, hip flask, fountain pen, lock of hair, oversize brittle photographs, photograph of Bertha Silver framed in glass (Flat-box 64)
  - Six 78 rpm sound recordings (acetate) of Silberschlag readings, 1947, 6.0 Folders (Box 65)
  - Correspondence w/Dalia Daniel; Photographs of Silberschlag and Daniel, ca. 1973-1986. (Box 52)
- Series IX. Photographs
  - Photographs, 7.0 Folders (Box 56)
  - Photographs, 8.0 Folders (Box 57)
- Series X. Postcards
  - Box 58: Postcards, 8.0 Folders (Box 58)
- Series XI. Programs/pamphlets/newsletters/flyers
  - Programs/pamphlets/newsletters/flyers (Box 59)
  - Programs/pamphlets/newsletters/flyers (Box 60)
  - Programs/pamphlets/newsletters/flyers (Box 61)
- Series XII. Unpublished writing by others
  - Playscript: We will never die, by Ben Hecht, n.d., ca. 1943; Playscript: Rahab of Jericho, by Harry Sackler, 1927; Playscript: Frankfort chronicle, by Harry Sackler, n.d.; Manuscript: Shirati, by Sh. Shalom, 11 p., n.d., 11.0 Folders (Box 62)
  - Papers from a symposium on Arab-Jewish Cultural Symbiosis, UT Austin, March 3-4, 1975, 10.0 Folders (Box 63)